Guide to the Doris Duke papers on the Duke Endowment, 1925-2001, bulk 1956-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Doris Duke papers on the Duke Endowment 1925-2001, bulk 1956-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke, Doris, 1912-1993
3.2 Linear Feet 2,400 Items
Doris Duke's father, James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, established the Duke Endowment as a perpetual charitable trust in 1924. Mr. Duke designed the fund to be both flexible and enduring, but limited its efforts to the Carolinas and to four program areas: child care, health care, higher education, and rural churches. Miss Duke became a trustee of the Endowment in 1933.
The collection spans the years 1925 to 2001, with the bulk dating from 1956 through 1993. Collection materials primarily document the administrative business of the Endowment and include correspondence, news stories, meeting materials, financial statements, legal records, reports, and proposals. Many of the materials relate specifically to the Endowment's interests in private university education and health care.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to portions of the records of The Duke Endowment is restricted. The Annual Report and other publications of The Duke Endowment or its divisions are open for research. Access to all other materials is restricted to trustees, officers, and staff of The Endowment and to researchers who have received prior written permission from The Endowment's president, chairman, or their designated representative. In addition, any researchers who are granted access to the materials must sign a statement indicating that they will not release the following information without prior written consent of the concerned individual or institution: (a) personally identifiable information about any living individual; or (b) institutionally identifiable information less than twenty-five years old about any institution still in existence.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Doris Duke papers on the Duke Endowment were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
Doris Duke's father, James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, established the Duke Endowment as a perpetual charitable trust with a $40 million gift on December 11, 1924. The Endowment was expanded by an additional $67 million upon Mr. Duke's death in 1925. Mr. Duke designed the fund to be both flexible and enduring, but limited its efforts to North and South Carolina and to four program areas: child care, health care, higher education, and rural churches. As stipulated by her father in the Indenture that created the Endowment, Miss Duke became a trustee of the Endowment when she reached the age of 21 in 1933. She took a special interest in children's issues and became Chairman of the Advisory Committee on Child Care Service in 1965. Though her level of involvement with the Endowment fluctuated over the years, Miss Duke served on many committees and remained a trustee until her death in 1993. Her offices continued to receive some official correspondence and annual reports through 2001.
Collection Overview
The Doris Duke papers on The Duke Endowment (formerly DE.10) are part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection spans the years 1925 to 2001, although the bulk of materials date from 1956 through 1993. Doris Duke served as a trustee of the Endowment from 1933 until her death in 1993. Collection materials primarily document the administrative business of the Endowment and include correspondence, invitations and solicitations, news stories, meeting materials, financial statements, legal records, reports, and proposals. Many of the materials relate specifically to the Endowment's interests in private university education and health care. Of particular interest are 21 published annual reports for years between 1939 and 2001, which detail efforts and expenditures in the four program areas J.B. Duke prescribed. The reports include personal stories, examinations of pressing issues, and photos of beneficiaries in later years, and the 1973 issue contains a 50th anniversary tribute to J.B. Duke and the Endowment.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke, Doris, 1912-1993
Duke Endowment
Endowments -- North Carolina
Doris Duke Charitable Foundation
Related Material
Duke Endowment Archives, 1902-2008 and undated, bulk 1925-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke Endowment Reference Collection, 1964-ongoing
University Archives, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Records, 1925-2001, bulk 1956-1993
  RESTRICTED: Selected materials in boxes 2-3 and 6-8 have access restrictions.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials of general business matters. 1926, 1933–1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials of general business matters. 1963–1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda from Miss Duke's office regarding the publication of a 40th anniversary book about The Duke Endowment. March 12, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Contact information, Trustees of The Duke Endowment. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials of general business matters. Includes letters about Doris Duke’s decision to waive commissions due to her from The Duke Endowment. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials of general business matters, including Summaries of Recommendations for hospital appropriations, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda to Doris Duke as a Trustee of The Duke Endowment. November 25, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda and proposal for application for the Archie Davis Scholarship for Nursing Excellence Fund, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1994 meeting calendar, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Invoices and vouchers relating to construction work performed at offices on the 57th Floor, 30 Rockefeller Plaza. 1956, 1961–1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial Statements. December 31, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Financial Statements. December 31, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, legal, to IRS to dispute rescindment of tax exemption status of The Duke Endowment, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Access restricted
  - Correspondence, legal, and related materials concerning legal advice on insider trading and new rules from the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC). 1989–1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, legal, concerning year-end reporting to the SEC of holdings of Duke Power Company stock. 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, The Duke Endowment, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, The Duke Endowment, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, The Duke Endowment, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, The Duke Endowment, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Meeting notice and related documents, Committee on Educational Institutions, November 7, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Meeting notice and related documents, Committee on Educational Institutions, November 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Meeting notice and related documents, Committee on Educational Institutions, October 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Meeting notice, minutes, and agenda, Committee on Educational Institutions, November 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Meeting notice and related documents, Committee on Educational Institutions, March 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Meeting notice and related documents, Committee on Educational Institutions, July 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Meeting notice, minutes, and agenda, Committee on Educational Institutions, October 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Meeting notice and related documents, Committee on Educational Institutions, November 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, October 2, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, November 7, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, March 7, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, April 4, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, July 9, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, August 31, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, October 5, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Meeting documents, The Duke Endowment Trustees, November 2, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Certified copies of Indenture and Deed establishing The Duke Endowment (1924) with additions by Will of James B. Duke (1925), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Judgment, Davis v. Davis. 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report. 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report. 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report. 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report. 1959 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report. 1961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report. 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report. 1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report. 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report. 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report. 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report. 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report. 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report. 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report. 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report. 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report. 1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report. 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report. 1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report. 2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report. 2001 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Proposals, requesting institutions to the Committee on Educational Institutions, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Proposals, requesting institutions to the Committee on Educational Institutions, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Reports, Committee on Educational Institutions, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reports, Committee on Educational Institutions (includes proposals from requesting institutions). 1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Reports, Committee on Educational Institutions (includes proposals from requesting institutions). August 1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Reports, Committee on Educational Institutions (includes proposals from Duke University only). December 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Reports, Committee on Educational Institutions (includes proposals from requesting institutions). December 1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Reports of the Investment Committee and other committees relating to the Duke Endowment, includes summaries of recommended Hospital Appropriations, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Reports of the Investment Committee and other committees relating to the Duke Endowment, includes summaries of Recommended Hospital and Child Care appropriations, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Report of the Secretary, The Duke Endowment, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Secretary, The Duke Endowment, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Secretary, The Duke Endowment, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Secretary, The Duke Endowment, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Report of the Secretary, The Duke Endowment, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Report of the Secretary, The Duke Endowment, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Report of the Treasurer, the Duke Endowment Agency Account, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Report of the Treasurer, the Duke Endowment Agency Account, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Report of the Treasurer, the Duke Endowment Agency Account, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Report, summaries from the four educational institutions assisted by The Duke Endowment. 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Self-Study Reports, The Duke Endowment. 1976 (1 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Self-Study Reports, The Duke Endowment. 1976 (2 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Self-Study Reports, The Duke Endowment. 1976 (3 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Report on expenditures of the 1983–1984 Special Education Grant to The Duke Endowment. 1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Booklet, "Indenture of James B. Duke establishing The Duke Endowment" (1932). n.d. (1 of 2) (3 copies) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Booklet, "Indenture of James B. Duke establishing The Duke Endowment" (1932). n.d. (2 of 2) (2 copies of newer version) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Addresses, The Fortieth Anniversary of The Duke Endowment. 1964 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin, Duke University, Financial Report, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Editorial, "James B. Duke and The Duke Endowment." November 25, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Questionnaires, shareholdings of Duke Power Company sent to Doris Duke. 1989–1991, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Alumni Register of Duke University. Features articles about James B. Duke and the creation of The Duke Endowment. December 1925 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Capital Campaign literature, Johnson C. Smith University. c. 1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Child Care, The Duke Endowment. 1961–1966 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Resolution For Presentation to the Trustees of The Duke Endowment, November 2, 1993" (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Printed materials, newspaper clippings from the Durham Sun and Durham Morning Herald regarding the opening of a new Duke Endowment office and a ceremony honoring W.C. Davison, Dean of Duke Medical School, upon his retirement, October 1-6, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 11)